Chapter 4: Hobby, games and fun
===============================

  * Programs, game and fun
    Online adventure games. The virus threat.
  * Hobbies. Holiday travels. Collecting stamps or coins.
    Roots, music, and online shopping.

Online services have one thing in common with newspapers, magazines
and books. What they offer, varies from provider to provider.
    The next chapters will focus on the contents of the offerings.
Appendix 1 has details about how to access the major service
providers.
    Small online services often have interesting offerings in
specialized areas, and especially when they are based on local
phenomena or events. They tend to be more personal. They often
present their 'wares' in a local language, and offer very large
collections of free software.
    The large online services have hundreds of thousands of users.
The activity is often high. They usually attract interesting (and
competent) participants to their conferences and forums, have more
programs available for download and more news sources and databases
to search. They generally give you a wider choice.
    We will focus on the large international services. These are
available from anywhere without too much effort, and using them
comes surprisingly cheap. Therefore, please remember that this book
just covers the top of the iceberg. Cheaper services may be found
elsewhere, and they may even be better tuned to your particular
areas of interest.

Locating game software
----------------------
The fastest, easiest and cheapest is to call an online service to
download game programs. You'll find an overwhelming number of
programs for all types of microcomputers.
    Many games are free. We call them "Public Domain" or "Freeware"
programs. Others are distributed free. You do not have to pay to
get them and try them out. If you want to use them, however, the
copyright owner expects you to pay a fee. We call them "shareware"
or "user supported" programs.
    When the game has been transferred to your personal computer,
you can play without worries about communications costs, or the
busy signal on your phone line.
    My favorite game is shareware. The name is Arachnid. It is an
MS Windows solitaire game (patience) made by SP Services, P.O. Box
456, Southampton, SO9 7XG, England. The desired registration fee is
UKP 15.00 (English pounds). You can download the program from my
board as WINCARD.EXE. The file is 106 kilobytes large.
    WINCARD.EXE is a special distribution file, which contains
three games and all supporting files. The EXE extension may fool
you into thinking that it is a program, and in a way it is. The
file is a self-extract file, meaning that you just enter "WINCARD"
on an MS-DOS computer to extract the game files from the "package."
    Games are usually distributed in such distribution files. All
files used by a game (or several games) is put into one file by
special software, and compressed in size. This makes retrieval of
programs easier and cheaper. You do not have to download many
related files individually. The transfer takes less time. (Read
about how to extract programs from distribution files in appendix
3).
    You will find some of the largest collections of games on the
North American services CompuServe and EXEC-PC BBS. You will also
find many throughout the Internet.

  | TRICKLE is a large collection of public domain and shareware   |
  | programs for MS-DOS, CPM, and other computers. For information |
  | about how to use TRICKLE, send a message through Internet to   |
  |                                                                |
  |         LISTSERV@VM1.NODAK.EDU                                 |
  |                                                                |
  | In the TEXT of the message write                               |
  |                                                                |
  |         /pdget pd:<msdos.starter>simtel20.inf                  |
  |                                                                |
  | An information file will be sent to your electronic mailbox.   |
  | (Read the chapter about electronic mail and appendix 1 for     |
  | more information.)                                             |
  |                                                                |
  | If TRICKLE is not enough, try Archie. It is the Internet       |
  | archive server listing service. The Archie database maintains  |
  | a list of roughly 1.5 million files containing 100 Giga-       |
  | bytes (that is, 100,000,000,000 bytes) of information          |
  | available from over 800 anonymous FTP archive sites.           |
  |     You can search this database by email to find where files  |
  | are located. Some Archie systems maintain a list of libraries  |
  | all over the world, while others concentrate on a more limited |
  | geographical area.                                             |
  |     Once Archie has told you where desired programs and files  |
  | are located, you can retrieve them by telnet, anonymous FTP,   |
  | of FTPmail. Read "File transfers through the Internet" in      |
  | chapter 12 for details.                                        |
  |     For information about using Archie, send mail to one of the|
  | following addresses (see appendix 4 for more options):         |
  |                                                                |
  |     archie@cs.mcgill.ca         (Canada)                       |
  |     archie@nic.funet.fi         (Finland)                      |
  |     archie@plaza.aarnet.edu.au  (Australia)                    |
  |                                                                |
  | Put the word HELP in the body of the mail                      |
  |                                                                |
  | Getting programs by email is a three-step process:             |
  | (1) Use Archie to find file names and where they are stored,   |
  | (2) Send a message to ftpmail@decwrl.dec.com to have them      |
  |     retrieved and forwarded to you by email, and               |
  | (3) Use a utility program to convert the file to a useful      |
  |     format. (See chapter 12.)                                  |
  |                                                                |
  | Check out JVArcServ for an Archie-alike service on FidoNet.    |

Chances are that online services in your area also have many
programs to offer. Most free bulletin boards have more software
than you'll ever get around to try.
    Usually, there is a natural specialization between boards.
Those using the Unix operating system, have the largest number of
programs for such machines. Those running on MS-DOS computers, have
more programs for such computers.
    Some games are trite and bad. Others are brilliant. There are
ladder games, games challenging your responses (racer car driving,
flight control, war games, subsea games), electronic versions of
traditional games like Backgammon, Yatzy, chess and bridge,
educational games (geography, mathematics and history), puzzles,
fractal programs (drawing beautiful pictures on your screen),
psychological tests, text-based adventure games, and other strange
and funny creations. Here is something for any taste or belief.
    If you want to get rich in a hurry, pick programs that increase
chances of winning horse race bets, or other "real world" money
winning games.
    If you're into beautiful girls, fill your hard disk with
picture files in GIF, PCX or other graphics formats. (Sorry ladies,
there are not many pictures of naked boys around.) You'll also find
software that will display the pictures that you just retrieved.
    Keen users of the more popular games often want to swap tricks
and discuss experiences: Super Nintendo players regularly meet on
the SNES mailing list (on SNES@spcvxa.spc.edu). To join, send your
subscription request to: SNES-Request@spcvxa.spc.edu .
    For chess, try the Chess Discussion List (CHESS-
L@GREARN.BITNET) unless Chinese Chess (on XIANGQI@INDYCMS.BITNET)
is what you're looking for. CompuServe has a Chess forum (GO
CHESSFORUM) with message sections called: Chess Basics, Theory &
Analysis, News Wire, Hardware/Software, Casual Games, Electronic
Knights, Oriental/Variants, Tourneys (Open), USCF Rated Games, Team
Play, and Time Out.
    Usenet excels when it comes to games:

  rec.gambling            Articles on games of chance & betting.
  rec.games.board         Discussion and hints on board games.
  rec.games.board.ce      The Cosmic Encounter board game.
  rec.games.bridge        Hobbyists interested in bridge.
  rec.games.chess         Chess & computer chess.
  rec.games.design        Discussion of game design related issues.
  rec.games.empire        Discussion and hints about Empire.
  rec.games.frp           Discussion about Role Playing games.
  rec.games.go            Discussion about Go.
  rec.games.hack          Discussion, hints, etc. about the Hack game.
  rec.games.misc          Games and computer games.
  rec.games.moria         Comments, hints, and info about the Moria game.
  rec.games.mud           Various aspects of multi-users computer games.
  rec.games.pbm           Discussion about Play by Mail games.
  rec.games.pinball       Discussing pinball-related issues.
  rec.games.programmer    Discussion of adventure game programming.
  rec.games.rogue         Discussion and hints about Rogue.
  rec.games.trivia        Discussion about trivia.
  rec.games.video         Discussion about video games.
  rec.games.video.arcade  Discussions about coin-operated video games.

With so many games and programs around, it is difficult to stay
current about new programs and new versions of old ones. Consider
subscribing to the MS-DOS Archive Additions (one-way) information
service. Internet MS-DOS archive managers use it to announce new
additions to their collections.
    To subscribe, send a message to LISTSERV@TACOM-EMH1.Army.Mil
with this command in the body of the message:


      subscribe msdos-ann

These announcements are also posted to the Usenet newsgroup called
comp.archives.msdos.announce .

  | It is probably easier for you to relate to references like     |
  | "rec.games.video on Usenet," than to XIANGQI@INDYCMS.BITNET.   |
  | References to BITNET mailing lists are made in various ways    |
  | throughout the book, just as it is online. This is the basic   |
  | rule:                                                          |
  |                                                                |
  | All BITNET mailing lists are 'managed' by a LISTSERV program,  |
  | which handles all subscription requests. When you read a       |
  | reference like XIANGQI@INDYCMS.BITNET, then that means that    |
  | a subscription request must be set to the LISTSERV at the      |
  | INDYCMS computer on BITNET. Mail to the forum, however, must   |
  | be sent to XIANGQI@INDYCMS.BITNET to be forwarded to the       |
  | other members.                                                 |
  |                                                                |
  | For more information about these strange address codes, and    |
  | how to use them, read about BITNET in appendix 1. You may      |
  | find it useful to read about email addresses in Chapter 7.     |
  |                                                                |
  | All BITNET mailing lists can be used by email through the      |
  | Internet. Several BITNET hosts also have Internet addresses.   |
  | Example: LISTSERV@NDSUVM1.BITNET can also be reached as        |
  | LISTSERV@vm1.nodak.edu . When dual addresses are given,        |
  | Internet users should use the Internet address, while BITNET   |
  | users should use the BITNET address.                           |
  |                                                                |
  | Note: In cases where a BITNET mailing list has dual addresses, |
  | we have usually given the Internet address. If you are on      |
  | BITNET, and using these addresses are difficult or impossible, |
  | ask your local postmaster for help.                            |

Computer viruses
----------------
Few online users ever live to see or experience a computer virus,
but they do exist. So, read this:
    A virus is a small, hidden computer program that can cause
the loss or alteration of programs or data, and can  compromise
their confidentiality. It can spread from program to program, and
from system to system, without direct human intervention.

    The chance of your computer being infected is small, but you're
never safe. Therefore, download a program for virus detection and
identification, like VIRUSSCAN from McAffee Associates, 4423
Cheeney Street, Santa Clara, CA 95054-0253, U.S.A. They also have
virus disinfection programs (for MS-DOS computers).
    For more about viruses, subscribe to VIRUS-L@LEHIGH.EDU.
CompuServe has the Mac New Users Forum (with a a Virus Clinic
section), the McAfee Virus Help Forum, the Symantec AntiVirus
Forum, and more. FidoNet has a VIRUS echo. ILINK has VIRUS-I.
Usenet has bit.listserv.valert-l (Virus Alert List), and
comp.virus .

Online games
------------
If you're into games, why not investigate online adventure games?
There are many alternatives. Prestel (England) offers TRASH, an
environmental multi-user game with a futuristic theme and full of
humor. Up to 64 persons can play simultaneously.
    " ...Callers play out the role of pandimensional refuse
disposal officers, whose primary aim in life is to clean up the
multiverse, as the Trash environment is called."
    "With a diverse range of 'psionic powers', which vary from
the nasty (pyrokinesis) to the gentle (faith healing), at their
command, Trash players roam across dimensions and universes,
completing various tasks."
    Bulletin boards throughout the world invite you to role playing
games. Some have graphics, music and sound effects. Dungeons &
Dragons is a popular choice.
    On EXEC-PC, play Startrek. Select an identity and "play it out"
according to its character. If you're a real afficionado, check out
rec.arts.startrek.info on Usenet or the list RASI-L@ncc1701e.uucp
(write LISTSERV@ncc1701e.uucp to subscribe).
    Advanced players swap tricks on STARGAME@PCCVM.BITNET. On many
BBSes, MUD is a most popular game.

  | Multi-User Dungeons (MUD) is a structured and user-modifiable |
  | online environment, which allows users not only to interact   |
  | with each other, but to do role-playing, build and furnish    |
  | living areas and interaction areas, extend and create the     |
  | interactive "space" and the rules for using that space.       |

Popular choices on CompuServe are strategy games like The Island of
Kesmai and Megawars. One game can last for weeks at a time. On CIX
(England), many prefer the multi-user dungeon game DiscWorld.
    If you prefer sport fantasies in the armchair, check out GEnie.
They offer Rotisserie League Baseball. Decide what team player to
be, and join in a match of American baseball.
    Nintendo offers online games through the Famicom Networks in
Japan and the U.S. Your PC must have a special graphics card to
play games like GO and Shogi, a Japanese game of chess.

Chat
----
Chat, or "keyboard talking," is a popular attraction, and in
particular on the large online services.
    Your first attempt will probably be a strange experience.
When may people talk simultaneously in chat mode, incoherent
sentences seem to fly over your computer screen. It takes some
training to be able to read what each of them is saying.
    CompuServe's Citizen Band Simulator (GO CB) is an electronic
version of the hams' short-wave radio. It has 72 CB Simulator
channels. You can chat with anonymous members, have fun and find
new keypals.
    On EXEC-PC's Chat and Entertainment System up to 64 users can
talk simultaneously. GEnie calls their service Livewire CB. On BIX,
look for CBIX.
    Some users are serious about chatting. Several large companies
are heavy users. Although this kind of talking is a slow process,
it has advantages. It is easy to document the discussion. People
from places geographically far apart can meet at a low cost to
discuss.
    Some online services charge less for chats than for other
services.

My hobby
--------
There are online forums for most hobbies: collection of stamps and
coins, genealogy, music, holiday travels, skiing, purchase of
consumer electronics, video, filming, and more.
    Those you meet in the clubs share your interests. They come to
exchange information and experiences, to listen, swap stamps or
coins, participate in club auctions, and exploit favorable group
discounts when buying things for their hobby.
    In these clubs, the main attraction is the open messages that
people write to each other. Many clubs also have libraries filled
with special software (like data base programs for collectors) and
information files.
    Coins (on Coins@rocky.er.usgs.gov) is a forum for discussion of
Numismatics, the study of coins, American and International.  Paper
currency is also a welcome topic, but trading is not allowed. To
subscribe, send a message to robert@whiplash.er.usgs.gov .

Music
-----
ILINK, an international exchange of conferences between bulletin
boards, has a forum for country music lovers. It presents itself
in these words:


     COUNTRY MUSIC
     Country & Western music including bluegrass and other related
     forms.  Discussion of artists, techniques, instruments &
     musicians.  Host: John Stewart


     One oasis of civility in the BBS maelstrom is the 150-board
     ILINK network -- recently renamed from InterLink.  Unlike most
     BBS networks, ILINK carefully evaluates each board before
     permitting membership.  "We are very selective -- some say
     overly selective," says ILINK's international host Andy Keeves.
     Choosiness keeps ILINK small but upholds the decorum of its
     message bases.

Usenet has rec.music.country.western . FidoNet has 60S_70S_PROGROCK
about the progressive rock music of the 60's and 70's, gospel music
in CHR_GSPL_MUSIC, a club for selling and buying between musicians
(MUSICIAN'S_SERVICES), and (MUSIC_COMP_101) for aspiring composers.
    CompuServe has a bunch of forums. Check out the Music/MIDI
sections in the Amiga and Atari ST Arts forums. The latter is a
full Music/MIDI forum. The Coin/Stamp/Collectibles Forum has a
section for music collectors.
    CompuServe's RockNet forum has the following structure:

       Available message sections:      Available file libraries:
        0 General/Misc.                    0 General Misc
        1 Rock Music                       1 Rock Music
        2 Rock Radio                       2 Rock Radio
        3 Reviews/LK                       3 Reviews
        4 Q&A/Help                         4 Q&A/Help
        5 Rock Film & Video                5 Rock Film & Video
        6 RockLetters                      6 RockLetters
        7 Trends                           7 Trends
        8 Heavy Metal                      8 Heavy Metal
        9 Old Wave                         9 Old Wave
       10 New Music                       10 New Music
       11 CD Hotline                      11 Compact Discs
       12 Green, Village                  12 Graphics/Programs

You can tailor your visits to RockNet to your personal interests.
If you're into Heavy Metal, limit your readings of messages to
those in section 8, and possibly 3 and 7.
    The Music and Performing Arts Forum (GO MUSICARTS) is another
interesting place on CompuServe. Converse with fellow music fans
about on topics like classical, jazz/blues, Big Band, country/folk
and religious music, ballet/dance, drama and more.
    MIDI is discussed on several bulletin boards, including in
conferences distributed by RelayNet.
    Classical music forums can be found on most larger services.
Try CLASSM-L on LISTSERV@BROWNVM.BITNET.
    For jazz, try the ILINK conference JAZZ, rec.music.bluenote on
Usenet, MILES on LISTSERV@HEARN.NIC.SURFNET.NL (about Miles Davis),
or BLUES-L at LISTSERV@BROWNVM.BROWN.EDU .
    Another jazz oriented list, SATURN on LISTSERV@HEARN.BITNET, is
for discussing the free-jazz big band leader, Sun Ra.
    Network-Audio-Bits is an electronic magazine bringing reviews
and information about rock, pop, new age, jazz, funk, folk music
and other genres. (Write Murph@Maine.BITNET to join.)
    The Music Newsletter offers reviews and interviews. Subscribe
by email to LISTSERV@VM.MARIST.EDU using the command "SUBSCRIBE
UPNEWS Your-full-name."

  | On BITNET mailing lists, you subscribe by using the command  |
  | "SUB <mailing-list-name> Your-full-name" in the body of your |
  | email.                                                       |
  |                                                              |
  | There are also mailing lists on Unix workstations, PCs, and  |
  | microVaxen. These may require that you write the subscribe   |
  | command in full ('SUBSCRIBE'), or use other commands.        |

To get the "Music List of Lists," an overview of music oriented
mailing lists, send email to mlol-request@wariat.org .
    GRIND (write grind-request@unh.edu) focuses on discussions
about grindcore/death metal/heavy thrash music. PRIMUS is about the
funk/rock band Primus (write to primus-request@unh.edu).
    KLARINET (on LISTSERV@VCCSCENT.BITNET) is a network bringing
news, information, research and teaching items of interest, and
other related information for clarinet players, teachers, students,
and enthusiasts.
    "Backstreets" on UUCP is for those who love the music of Bruce
Springsteen (backstreets-request@virginia.edu). "Eclipse" (eclipse-
request@beach.cis.ufl.edu) focuses on Pink Floyd and his music. If
a fan of Jimi Hendrix, join "hey-joe" (hey-joe-request@ms.uky.edu).
    In "brass," the topic is brass band music (write to brass-
request@geomag.gly.fsu.edu for access).
    "J-Pop" (jpop-request@wystan.bsd.uchicago.edu via UUCP) has
discussions about Japanese pop/rock of today.

Wine and food
-------------
Some people would rather fill their stomachs than their ears. They
call CompuServe for the Cooks Online forum (for gourmets) and the
Bacchus Wine Forum (for their throats).
    BITNET has the mailing list "Eat" (EAT-L@VTVM2), a club for
FoodLore/Recipe Exchange. In J-FOOD-L (J-FOOD-L@JPNKNU10 on BITNET)
they discuss Japanese food and culture.
    If your interest is more academic, subscribe to FOODWINE (on
LISTSERV@CMUVM.CSV.CMICH.EDU). It is for those seriously interested
in the academic study of food and its accompaniments in the 1990's,
including a variety of disciplines, such as marketing,
communications, hospitality, consumer affairs, hotel and catering
management.
    Usenet has rec.food.cooking, rec.food.recipes, rec.food.drink,
rec.food.restaurants, and rec.food.veg for vegetarians. On FidoNet,
check out INTERCOOK for words of wisdom on International Cooking.
    On ILINK and RelayNet, look for CUISINE. That is where we found
the following recipe for Mexican Meatloaf:

        2 lb Ground Beef
        1 ea Bell Pepper, Diced
   10 1/2 oz Cream Chicken Soup
       10 oz Cheddar Cheese
        4 oz Green Chilies, Diced
        1 ea Onion, Chopped
        8 oz Taco Sauce
        1 pk Tortillas
        4 oz Mushrooms (fresh optional)
        2 ea Jalapen"'s (to taste)

  1. Brown ground beef and drain.
  2. Mix onions, green peppers, mushrooms, green CHILIES, taco
     sauce, jalapen"'s and cream chicken soup into skillet with
     ground beef.
  3. Simmer until vegetables are soft.
  4. Shred cheddar cheese.
  5. In crock pot or dish, layer meat mixture, cheese, and
     tortillas; heat until cheese melts.

Bon apetit!

Outdoor life
------------
CompuServe's Great Outdoors SIG is for those preferring nature for
the computer screen. Its sections are called:

  General/Photography, Scouting, Power Boating, TROUT UNLIMITED,
  Fishing, Hunting, Cycling, AUDUBON/Birding, Canoe/Kayak/Raft,
  Camp/Hike/Walk/RV, Snow Sports/Climb, OWAA, CIS/Computers,
  Firearms, NRA, Environmnt/Wildlife, OUTDOOR LIFE mag.

If you dream of visiting Alaska to hunt, fish and explore the
wilderness by canoe, then this is the place. Add the Outdoor
Cooking section of the Cooks Online Forum to make it perfect.
    Scandinavian bulletin boards exchange the "JAKT_FRILUFT"
conference (Through MIX). ILINK offers OUTDOORS, which focuses
on outdoor hobbies.
    As usual, Usenet has a lot. These are some examples:

  rec.aviation        Aviation rules, means, and methods.
  rec.backcountry     Activities in the Great Outdoors.
  rec.bicycles        Bicycles, related products and laws.
  rec.birds           Hobbyists interested in bird watching.
  rec.boats           Hobbyists interested in boating.
  rec.boats.paddle    Talk about any boats with oars, paddles,
                      etc.
  rec.climbing        Climbing techniques, competition
                      announcements, etc.

Scouts participate in SCOUTER on FidoNet (International SCOUTING
Conference) and SCOUTS-L (SCOUTS-L@NDSUVM1) on BITNET. Golfers meet
in GOLF-L (on LISTSERV@ubvm.bitnet).
   Photo enthusiasts will track down PHOTO-L@BUACCA.BITNET,
CompuServe's Photography Forum and its SCUBA Forum's sections for
underwater photography. For more, there's "Photography" on EXEC-PC
and The Well, PHOTO on RelayNet, PHOTOSIG on ILINK and rec.photo on
Usenet.
    If you're into 3-d (stereo) photography, enroll in "3d" on
UUCP:

    Contact: 3d-request@bfmny0.bfm.com (Tom Neff)
    Purpose: Discussion of 3-D (stereo) photography. General info,
    hints, experiences, equipment, techniques, and stereo
    "happenings."  Anyone interested is welcome to join.

There are clubs for all popular outdoor hobbies.

Roots
-----
On ROOTS-L@NDSUVM1.BITNET and soc.roots on Usenet, the emphasis is
on genealogy. Here, you'll get tips about tools and techniques. You
can exchange information about ancestors and find new friends and
partners for joint research.
    On CompuServe, it is called The Genealogy Forum. One message
section is called Overseas Ancestry. Remember to check out the
Family History Library, a newsletter bringing news from the library
for genealogical research in Salt Lake City, U.S.A. (stored in
Library 10.)
    The North American bulletin boards ROOTS-BBS (San Francisco)
and THE FAMILY ROOTS (Oklahoma) are connected to FidoNet.
    GEnie has the Genealogy Knowledgebase. FidoNet has

     GENDATA               Genealogy Database
     GENEALOGY:_WGW        Who's Got What (WGW) Data Base
     GENSOFT               Genealogy software
     SE_GENEALOGY          South Eastern US Genealogy Conference

Since FidoNet has links all over the world, these conferences can
give contacts in countries that you might otherwise have problems
in reaching.
    On most of these services, you'll find interesting genealogy
programs and files with practical hints about how to write a book
about your family.

Him and Her
-----------
Members of the female sex have their favorite meeting places, like
Cleopatra on Bergen By Byte. Men do not have admission.
    Usenet has soc.feminism. Those with limited access to Usenet,
may subscribe to "feminism-digest." Send email to feminism-
digest@ncar.ucar.edu to get on the mailing list.

    "Contact feminism-digest@ncar.ucar.edu" above means that you
    need to write a message to this Internet email address with a
    subscription request, or to receive further information about
    how to join. This mailing list does not have automatic
    subscriptions.

To join the mailing list "feminists," write Patricia Collins on
collins@hplabs.hp.com . She presents the conference's purpose in
this way:

    The feminist mailing list is intended to provide a forum
    for discussion of issues of interest to women, in a friendly
    atmosphere. The basic tenets of feminism and the day-to-day
    experiences of women do not have to be explained or defended.
    Men and women can join, but everyone requesting to be added to
    the mailing list MUST provide the moderator with: (1) a full
    name; (2) a complete UUCP path to a well-known host or a fully
    specified Internet address; (3) the correspondent's gender (for
    records and statistics only).  NO exceptions.

While we're at it, let's move on to other topics associated with
the term sex:
    Bisexuals can participate in "sappho" on UUCP. Contact
sappho-request@mc.lcs.mit.edu. On BITNET, you'll find BIFEM-L
(BIFEM-L@BROWNVM), BISEXU-L (BISEXU-L@BROWNVM) and others.
    Spanish speaking users can subscribe to ARENAL (Lista de
discussion para hispanos/as que desean acabar con la homofobia).
Subscribe by email to LISTSERV@LUT.FI .
    Usenet has tons of it: soc.motss, alt.politics.homosexuality,
alt.sex.bestiality, alt.sex, alt.sex.bondage, alt.sex.pictures.d,
clari.news.group.gays, alt.sex.pictures, alt.sex.motss,
clari.feature.kinsey (Sex Q&A and Advice from Kinsey Institute),
clari.news.law.crime.sex and clari.news.sex.
    Conferences called "SEXUALITY" are alive on FidoNet and The
Well. CompuServe has a Human Sexuality Adult Forum and a Human
Sexuality Open Forum. STOPRAPE@BROWNVM.BITNET is a Sexual Assault
Activist List.
    Finally, there are a large number of pictures of nudes in all
possible and impossible positions. Most of them are childish, some
are decidedly pornographic, a few are beautiful and erotic.
    The online services' policies vary about what kind of
pictures and picture programs to make available. The larger the
service, the more conservative they tend to be.

Programs for hobbyists
----------------------
It's no rule that a service need to have a conference about a
hobby, to have interesting programs available for downloading.
Programs float around from service to service much easier than
conference items. Still, the best programs for a given hobby are
normally found on services where hobbyists meet to discuss.
    You will find:

    Chess and bridge programs,
    Morse code training programs for ham amateurs,
    Astrology programs,
    Data base systems for keeping track of music cassettes or
      records, video cassettes, books, stamps, coins, etc.
    Information systems for wine lovers,
    Recipe programs (tell me what you've got, and I'll tell
      you what you can make), and much more.

Online shopping
---------------
You can buy almost anything online: video cameras, books, music,
Bonsai plants, golf equipment, canned cakes from Gimmee Jimmy's
Cookies, Levi's trousers for men, computer equipment, a four-door
Nissan Pathfinder SE-V6 car, and air tickets for Mexico.
    Shoppers who let their modem do the "walking" are already a few
steps ahead of people Still stuck shopping the old-fashioned way.
Experienced online shoppers know that you can tap a world of stores
without ever leaving your keyboard, and that you can browse and buy
with very little effort.
    Some services present their wares "for your information only."
It's like reading newspaper ads. You must contact the seller to
buy. Other services have large online supermarkets with many
stores, and you can by while you visit.
    Subscribers to CompuServe get a monthly magazine by mail. "Go
Mall Shoppers' Guide" is a regular insert with color photos and
descriptions of selected products. Type GO MALL, order a product,
enter your credit card number, and have it sent you by mail.
    What if used goods are good enough? ILINK, the international
conference exchange system, has GARAGESALE. Here you can buy and
sell for hobby or home: Photo, video, audio, sound/music and midi
equipment, and all kinds of other domestic items. ILINK also has
a conference called BUY-SELL.
    HAM-SALE on the FidoNet is for ham amateurs wanting to swap, by
or sell. The American computer magazine PC Week is operating a
Buyer's Forum on CompuServe.
    UUCP's "muscle-cars" is where "muscle car" enthusiasts offer
advice, share problems and solutions, discuss technical issues,
racing, buying or selling parts, cars, or services, or just discuss
cars and swap stories with others. (Contact: muscle-cars-
request@sorinc.PacBell.COM).
    Similar experiences are waiting for you in "BMW" (Write: bmw-
request@sol.crd.ge.com), "british-cars" (Write: british-cars-
request@encore.com), "italian-cars" (Write: italian-cars-
request@sol.crd.ge.com) and "Z-cars" (the topic is Z-cars from
Datsun/Nissan. Write: rsiatl!z-car-request).
    Vintage VW (at VintageVW@rocky.er.usgs.gov) is about Vintage
Volkswagens. This includes the Beetle, Bus (Types II and II/IV),
Ghia, Squareback, Kubelwagen (Thing), bajas, buggies, Schwimmwagen,
rails and any VW (air-cooled) powered vehicle including aircraft.
    Beginners, gurus, mechanics and non-mechanics, restorers and
daily drivers are welcomed. This is where you can discuss how-to
stuff, parts availability, answer mechanical questions, list show
dates, swap meets, club addresses, favorite stories, etc. To
subscribe, send a message to robert@whiplash.er.usgs.gov .
    The newsletter NEWSBYTES brings you regular reports about
prices on used computers from The Boston Computer Exchange (BOCO).
The newsletter is available through GEnie, ZiffNet on CompuServe,
NewsNet, Dialog, and others.
    ZiffNet also offers the Computer Directory, an online
encyclopedia with information about more than 75,000 hardware
and software products sold in North America (1993). The data base
is updated monthly.

Planning your holidays
----------------------
CompuServe invites you to read reviews of theater performances,
books, movies and restaurants, opera, symphonies, ballets, dance,
museums and art galleries. They have information about airline
schedules and prices, hotels and the latest ski weather forecast.
    Televerket's Datatorg in Norway offers air tickets and hotel
reservations through SMART LINK, a self-serve system operated by
the Norwegian travel agencies. Entertainment and travel are also
popular on Prestel. Most British tour operators have an "office"
there.
    Several international services, including CompuServe and Dow
Jones News/Retrieval, offer OAG (The Official Airline Guide) and
Eaasy Sabre (the American Airlines reservation system).
     Worldscan/Travel shopper is on CompuServe and Delphi. The
Travel Forum on CompuServe administers a member travel discount
program. Download HOTEL.SAV in Library 0 for information about
lower rates on hotel room and car-rental rates.
    It's often possible to book hotel rooms and rent cars online.
Travelshopper has a built-in hotel guide, searchable by city around
the world. OAG has a database of over 40,000 hotels worldwide
(1992). It has the AA Rated European Hotels & Restaurants menu,
which covers trips from Andorra to Yugoslavia. Accu-Weather
provides three-day weather forecasts for 450 cities worldwide,
updated hourly.
    Travel agents are also operative through the Internet. One
alternative is at TRAVEL@delphi.com . Telnet lib.dartmouth.edu for
a World Factbook on countries.
    Is this your first visit to Japan? Why not prepare your visit
through the online service TWICS in Tokyo. It presents itself like
this:

  "Japan is an island nation, full of communities in villages,
  towns, and cities squeezed in between the mountains and the sea,
  with ports of various sizes and shapes through which communication
  flows between communities.

  Our own online community is organized in the same terms, an
  island community "BEEJIMA" (Bee Island), with our village
  ("MURA"), a port ("MINATO"), and our very own volcanic mountain
  ("YAMA").

  In the village, there is a village office ("YAKUBA"), a community
  meeting place ("YORIAI"), a high-tech corner ("AKIHABARA") named
  after the famous electronics district in Tokyo, a health center
  ("EMEDICA"), a place to hang around and read things ("HON YA"), a
  school ("GAKKOU"), and a market ("ICHIBA"). The port has holding
  areas and leads to other parts of Japan ("NIPPON") and the world
  ("SEKAI").  The mountain has a hot springs ("ONSEN") recreational
  area, and a lively outdoor bath ("IN THE OFURO") which has become
  the social center of our island.

Add to this soc.culture.japan on Usenet, the BITNET discussion list
JAPAN@NDSUVM1, the Japan Forum on CompuServe, and "JAPAN" on
RelayNet.
    Did you say the former "Soviet Union?" Here are phone numbers
to some "local" bulletin board systems:

    Moscow Fair (Moscow):                   +7 095 366 5209
    SUEARN NIC BBS (Moscow):                +7 095 938 3618
    Kreit BBS (Leningrad):                  +7 812 112 2611
    Amber Way BBS (Vilnius, Lithuania):     +7 012 222 7194
    UFO BBS (Riga, Latvia):                 +7 013 232 3983
    Post Square #1 (Kiev, Ukrain):          +7 044 417 5700

BITNET club TRAVEL-L (TRAVEL-L@TREARN) for those interested in
tourism. ILINK and The Well have conferences under the name TRAVEL.
    Many conferences in online land concentrate on particular parts
of the world. BALT-L@UBVM.BITNET is focusing on the Baltic states.
In AFRICA-L@BRUFPB.BITNET they discuss Africa. On Usenet, the news
group is called soc.culture.african.
    To brush up your Portuguese, consider joining BRAS-NET, It is a
Brazilian mailing list/network. Send your subscription request to
bras-net-request@cs.ucla.edu . For general information about other
Brazilian interest groups, write LISTSERV@FAPQ.FAPESP.BR .
    For those who are into Spanish, why not check out CHILE-L
(at LISTSERV@USACHVM1.BITNET), or FOLLAC, a mailing list about
'Folklore Latino, Latinoamericano y Caribeno'. To join, write Emily
Socolov at owner-follac@ccwf.cc.texas.edu .
    Here are some other African sources: the French language
Algeria News List (ALGNEWS) is on LISTSERV@gwuvm.gwu.edu. TUNISNET
(on LISTSERV@psuvm.psu.edu) is The Tunisia Network. EGYPT-NET
(write: egypt-net-request@das.harvard.edu) is the Egypt Discussion
and News forum.
    Send mail to mcgee@epsilon.eecs.nwu.edu to get a list of
Internet/Bitnet mailing lists that focus on African, African-
American, African-Caribbean or African-Latin issues, and a list of
African information sites.
    In the soc.culture hierarchy on Usenet, you'll find area codes
like asian, african, arabic, asean, australian, bangladesh,
british, canada, china, celtic, europe, filipino, french, german,
greek, hongkong, indian, iranian, italian, jewish, korean, latin-
american, lebanon, magyar, nepal, new-zealand, nordic, pakistan,
polish, soviet, spain, sri-lanka, taiwan, thai, turkish, vietnamese
and yugoslavia.
    In "argentina," you can read about how to make empanadas while
sharpening up your Spanish before visiting Buenos Aires. (Contact:
argentina-request@ois.db.toronto.edu).
    CompuServe's Travel Forum has sections called United States,
Canada, Mexico/Central America, Caribbean, South America, Oceania,
Asia, Europe, Africa/Middle East and Hawaii.
    If you're off to London, check out the UK Travel section in
CompuServe's UK Computing Forum. Its library contains files with
tips about affordable hotels, British road signs, and a list of
London theatre shows with ticket-buying tips.
    If your destination is Germany, practice Deutch in the Deutches
Forum (GO GERNET).
    Search for additional background information using CompuServe's
Magazine Database Plus, if you don't mind paying a wee surcharge.
Look up places to stay in the ABC Worldwide Hotel Listing.
    On America Online, you can research National Geographic and
National Geographic Traveler Magazines online. You can look up your
destination in the electronic Comptons Encyclopedia.
    GEnie has a Japan RoundTable and a Deutchland RoundTable.
Both provide for interaction with users from those respective
countries.
    If you are responsible for your company's business travels,
check out the following newsletters on NewsNet: BUSINESS TRAVEL
NEWS, and TOUR & TRAVEL NEWS. (You can also search NewsNet's
newsletters through CompuServe's IQuest, Dialog, and others).
    NewsNet has searchable newsletters focusing on the conditions
in particular countries or parts of the world (news, travel and
political risk analysis, political stability, etc.).

Politics
--------
Many of these conferences and forums are filled to the brim with
political discussions. For information about the United Nations,
subscribe to UN (on LISTSERV@INDYCMS.IUPUI.EDU).
